A Guide to the Papers of Jane C. Slaughter 1809-1951
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Jane C. Slaughter 1809-1951
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3700, -a, -b
This collection consists of ca. 1500 items (approximately 3.2 shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were originially given to the University of Virginia Library on May 1, 1951 by Captain and Mrs. R.I. Slaughter of Silver Spring, Maryland. The donors gave additional papers on May 10, 1951. On June 16, 1975 the Library received additional pieces from Arthur Workman of Portsmouth, Ohio.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of about 3.2 shelf feet (ca. 1500 pieces) and includes the legal, financial, genealogical, and personal papers of Jane Chapman Slaughter, a genealogical authority and one of the first women to receive a Ph.D. from the University of Virginia. These papers cover the years 1809-1951 and consist of the correspondence of both Miss Slaughter and her family, her M.A. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation, genealogical records, photographs, notebooks, drawings, newspaper clippings, and diplomas.
Jane Chapman Slaughter was born in Virginia in 1860. She graduated from the college of William and Mary in 1910. After teaching school for a number of years she returned to the College of William and Mary where she obtained an M.A. degree in 1923. In 1935 she earned a Ph.D. in Romance Languages from the University of Virginia at the age of 75. Her dissertation topic was "Louis Hue Girardin, Educator, Historian, and Man- Of-Letters."
While this collection is largely of a personal nature, it is useful for both the family historian and genealogist interested in stuyding a prominent Virginia family. In addition, there are transcripts of 38 letters from Thomas Jefferson to Louis Hue Girardin covering the years 1809-1823, which Miss Slaughter used in writing her dissertation.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The papers have been arranged in the following order: personal correspondence of Jane Slaughter, family correspondence, academic and miscellaneous works of Jane Slaughter, school notebooks, genealogical material (including papers, notebooks, scrapbooks, photographs, newspaper clippings, and family crests), legal papers, financial records, miscellaneous papers, and diplomas earned by members of the Slaughter family.
Organization
As the material in the two additions was very similar to that of the original accession, all three collections have been interfiled.
Contents List
- Typed transcripts of letters from Thomas Jefferson to L[ouis]; H[ue] Girardin 1809-1823, 36 pieces (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Miss Jane C. Slaughter 1905-1949, 66 pieces (Box 1)
  All but one apparently to Miss Slaughter and all or nearly all on genealogy.
- Jane Chapman Slaughter, Velasquez and his Art, ms. copy of M.A., thesis, College of William and Mary 1923, 1 piece (Box 1)
- Jane Slaughter, notes and draft of Ph.D. dissertation n.d., 1 piece, ca. 150 pp. (Box 1)
- Jane Slaughter, notebook on Girardin and Stricker1932, 1 piece (Box 1)
- Correspondence on Slaughter family etc. 1863-1951, 1858-1927, 39 pieces, 47 pieces (Box 1)
  Miscellaneous including a letter from Lady Astor, i.e. Nancy
- Correspondence of Jane Slaughter 1880-1900, 70 pieces (Box 1)
  Nearly all correspondence of male Slaughters, probably of the generation before Miss Jane's, and apparently all on genealogy.
- Jane Chapman Slaughter Louis Hue Girardin, Educator, Historian and Man-Of-Letters, typed copy of Ph.D. dissertation, University of Virginia. 1940, 1 piece. (Box 2)
- Jane Chapman Slaughter, typed MSS contributed to Harper's 125th anniversary contest. n.d. (Box 2)
  The subjects of the six biographical studies are Louis Hue Girardin; Captain Philip Pendleton Slaughter of Culpeper County; Thomas Towles Slaughter of Orange County; Rev. Philip Slaughter of Culpeper County; Anne Mercer Slaughter of Culpeper County; and Lieutenant Vivian Slaughter of 20th London Battalion.
- Jane Slaughter, mostly biographical sketches, a few songs. n.d., 12 pieces (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, Velasquez and His Art, 2 essays n.d., I ms and one typed, 2 pieces (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, sketches, mostly heraldic. n.d., 18 pieces. (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, miscellaneous sketches, poems. n.d., MSS, 50 pieces (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, sketchbook. 1872-1886, 1 piece (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, biography of Rev. Philip Slaughter n.d., Ms., 1 piece (Box 2)
- Jane Slaughter, books of sketches in pencil. (Box 3)
  ca. 1883-1884 (some titled); ca. 1885-1890 (some titled); ca. 1878 (a number titled, one a self-potrait at age 18); ca. 1878 (some titled); ca. 1873 (some titled); ca. 1873 (some titled); ca. 1872 (some titled); ca. 1877 (some titled); ca. 1891-1894 (some titled); n.d.
- Notes for a paper on Durand ca. 1926, MS (Box 3)
- Another cleaner copy of Durand paper n.d., MS (Box 3)
- French excercises; Fraser and Squair text 1927 (Box 3)
- Notebook, Old French 1902 (Box 3)
- French notebook 1924-1925 (Box 3)
- Jane Slaughter, Latin Notebook, Tr of Vergil's Aeneid1913 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, English grammar notebook, UVA 1916 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical and biographical notes n.d. (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, school notebook, test grades, etc. 1919-1920 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, school notebook, test 1918-1919 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, school notebook, tests, etc. 1917-1918 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, school notebook, mostly Latin 1913-1917 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, notebook, etc., thesis notes. 1929-1930 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, grade book 1927-1928 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, tests, grades, etc. 1927-1928 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, tests, grades, etc. 1923-1924 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, tests. 1927-1928 (Box 4)
- Jane Slaughter, grade book. 1926-1927 (Box 4)
- Notebook, partly a diary, partly surveyor's and other notes, all pencil, the first pages badly faded. References to M and O R.R. ca. 1857. (Box 4)
- Genealogical papers, a paper on Governor Spotswood n.d., ca. 40 pieces (Box 5)
- Letters to H.S. Slaughter, M. Slaughter, and Mrs. Charles Sweet Johnson on genealogy 1894, 1896, n.d. (Box 5)
- Fragment of a typed letter, critique of a MS (to Janie Slaughter?) n.d. (Box 5)
- Genealogical notes, etc. n.d., ca. 27 pieces (Box 5)
- Genealogical notes, essays. n.d., ca. 27 pieces (Box 5)
- Essays of various kinds. n.d., ca. 9 pieces (Box 5)
- Genealogical and essays. n.d., ca. 72 pieces (Box 5)
- Jane Slaughter, notebook, genealogical notes, including copies of family letters. 1936 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, heraldry notes 1901 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical copies of family letters n.d. (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical, etc. ca. 1926 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical, etc. ca. 1933-1934 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical, etc. ca. 1942 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical, etc. n.d. (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical notes. 1901-1903 (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical notes. n.d. (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical notes n.d. (Box 6)
- Jane Slaughter, genealogical notes ca. 1931 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, genealogical. n.d. (Box 7)
- Photos, negatives, sketches, etc., 24 pieces (Box 7)
- Drawings of arms, etc., 116 pieces (Box 7)
- Genealogical scrapbook, heraldic devices, etc. n.d. (Box 7)
- Coats of arms, etc. n.d., 126 pieces (Box 7)
- J.C. Slaughter legal papers; will, deed, etc. 1924-1951, 10 pieces (Box 8)
- Bills, receipts, etc. 1865-1951, ca. 75 pieces (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous ca. 1887-1942, 30 pieces (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous ca. 1855-1948, 30 pieces (Box 8)